Rocío Vidal, also known as "Schrödinger's Cat", journalist and
science popularizer. Thank you very much for
granting us this interview.
-It's a pleasure, it's a real pleasure.
Well, you are one of the very few well-known people
in Spain and Latin America, who openly declare themselves atheists,
and who openly treat religions as falsehoods.
In the United States and Great Britain, this is quite common,
there are quite a few people who do it, but not here, why
do you think this could be?
-It's funny, really funny.
Before starting my YouTube channel, I
have seen many debates that have been made in the United States by
great speakers, for example the one with Sam Harris versus Jordan
Peterson that lasts six hours or something like that, and I watched it all.
And it seemed fascinating to see how people with
opposing or different ideas about religion could
debate so politely and so openly and yet in
Spain or Latin America I didn't see those parallel examples,
in Latin America and it seemed curious to me. The truth is
that I do not have an answer for that, the United States are even
more religious than Spain. Perhaps here we have created
that motto of "live and let live", do not mess with the
affairs of the believers, because we are not
bothering each other too much to live together in peace. I believe that it is not
incompatible creating a healthy or open debate on the bases
of religion or how it affects our daily lives
with respecting each other, I believe that coexistence is
clearly necessary, but debate and rational discussion
on certain aspects can also be very
positive.
-Your video "God is dead" was
demonetized, so the ability for
this video to generate income for you was taken away. -Then they
monetized it again.
-Yes I know, but what happened? Did this
only happen with this video?
Not at all! It happens to me continuously.
-Ah, okay.
Of course, the theme of my channel is sometimes
very tricky, right? Because in the end I deal with controversial issues
regarding religion but also other pseudosciences.
So let's say YouTube doesn't like controversial content
too much. Then first it demonetizes you.
Not all of them, but it's true that God's one was like
"Forget about monetizing it!" I had to fight like this:
Let's see, can you tell me that what I said was disrespectful, offen, of
course I offend someone, but that shouldn't be a
reason to demonetize either, right? But in the end, fighting and
fighting, they ended up monetizing it for me, it's the story of
my channel. Wow, how impressive. Yes.
I am struck when we say "God is dead" or
talk about God, by the capital G for God. Before,
gods had names, right?
But this capitalized gods seem like a resource so that everything is permitted.
"I think that "God" exists", And how do you take that away? How do you argue? Because whoever
has an idea will say "No, the God I'm talking about is like this or like that..."
Doesn't this make it impossible to talk about it?
Shouldn't we say: Hey, which god?
That makes it very
complicated, because I believe that there are as many gods as there are
people, you when you talk to believers, that person
talks to you about his/her god, in the way that person understands that god,
which can differ a lot from another person and the idea that she/he
has of that god, and the ideas that her/his god defends or promulgates, right? So, it's okay, let's talk about what we are
discussing, I think that an inevitable
gap is created between when we talk about beliefs, and what we
believe for a god, when we talk about religions,
their role in society, if it does more harm than good, or more
good than harm, then I think it's a bit of a separate debate
, right? A more abstract debate, right? More philosophical
about that idea of ​​God, to what extent can we believe in
God, it is mere faith, there is evidence, there is no evidence, that is
a debate. And another debate is what is happening with
religion today? How are atheists or believers of other religions
persecuted ? What's going on in that? You
have to separate because it becomes an amalgam of
debates that is impossible to specify.
-Just as
pseudosciences and pseudo therapies are recognized as
a problem by all people, say, skeptical,
scientific, religions that are also a pseudo-knowledge, a
pseudo-philosophy, a pseudo-ethics, in some cases
quite horrible, are not seen as a problem, people only talk
about respect. When are we going to recognize that they are a problem?
The belief in something by faith, the thousands of abstract beliefs,
more concrete, more absurd, more dangerous, when are we going to
recognize this as a problem and deal with it? Because this is not being
treated as a problem, as well as the pseudosciences.
Absolutely, for example, religion has
obtained as an immunity that I think is totally
undeserved compared to other beliefs that we do put much more in
doubt and in check. However, religion is something you do not
touch, something that affects so many millions of people
that causes persecution throughout the world, wars,
deaths, intolerance, suffering in many people,
how is it possible that this acquires such a prerogative that
when you get into that topic, they tell you: "Why don't you let
people believe what they want? Of course! But that
is not incompatible with the fact that we can have a debate on
to what extent it is imposed. Well that's a fact isn't it?
But how they impose on us since we are kids, the belief in a superior being
that we have... that is like coming out of the closet, in the
end, to a certain extent,
you have to have that own reflection and
that critical thinking to question what they have
imposed on you, so why don't we move towards a model in which
children are told that they can believe whatever they want?
Then, they can fill in whatever they want with magical thinking,
I respect that as long as you don't try to impose that belief or that
thought of yours on other people, right? Like what
has always been done, well with Catholic morality, here in Spain,
right? For example, with Catholic and Christian morality, right?
Now we are starting to get rid of it, but
until now it was the discipline that had to be
followed necessarily. So, less "necessarily," and more
critical thinking, I think. In a respectful way, of course.
And I also see it a bit naive to say: "Ok,
if you believe that..." But if you believe, you are
convinced that there is a higher being, that you are going to go to
heaven, or anything, obviously you are going to teach
that to your children. So, "as long as you don't try to impose..."
If an idea is in your head, it will always
try to spread, right?
-Of course. Of course, but
parents indoctrinate children in all possible beliefs, such as
political orientation. You also tell a child... ¿Which values ​​do you impose on
her/him?  Well, if your parents are right-wing, then in the end the
child will learn that, it is It is very difficult to establish the
line of what I teach my son, or not.
It's also very important that schools teach the possibility of criticism,
so that they can free themselves a little if they have
parents, which in the end this is inevitable, that they
are more prone to indoctrinate their children in certain beliefs,
that is a problem that goes in so many areas
also outside of religion that it seems very complicated to me.
Well, the difference would be perhaps that
just as in politics, you from the first moment see that
there are several political options and your parents tell you: "That's the
good one." Yes, but you see that there is discussion. But with religion your parents say,
"This is it." And you see little confrontation, little debate, for
what we were talking.
-Exactly, that's why it would be good to see it in
the classroom, and among your classmates that this debate is created, also
like the issue of sexual orientation, we children
believe that boys have to like girls, and
girls like children. When we grow up, maybe the light comes to
us , someone says something to us, we say: "Wow, maybe
I didn't have to like boys!" And you see the light,
unfortunately it is like that, if from a young age we created a
sexual education, and an education in critical thinking in general,
then many problems would be solved, I think.
I see that about thirty years ago,
acupuncture, homeopathy, other pseudosciences, and pseudotherapies
were practically anecdotal, they were not known, but look how we are now:
More than half the population,
practically, believes in all these things. Or, for example,
things like the Islamic veil, which people laughed at, in
countries where the situation is now dramatic, they laughed:
"They tell me to put on the veil" ..., and now go there, tell them not to wear it...
I see that people believe that
religion is already declining, but it seems that the
data says it is not, right? It seems that the data in the world say
that religions are growing dramatically and especially
Islam, which is a very very aggressive religion, right?
-Absolutely. Are we not aware of this danger,
when people are so passive about this issue?
When it does not touch us very closely, we are not so
aware, because of course, it is true that in the West, in
Europe it is declining, at least, or in Spain,
there are more and more atheists, more agnostics, and yes, we notice it.
But it is true that if we look at the world's figures,
religion has more and more followers, and also because more and more of us are born
and we are overpopulating the world so of course it is a problem, and in parallel all this type of
alternative beliefs go very hand in hand with all this because
in the end we have created a type of societies in which the most aggressive religious
doctrine is rejected by young people, right?
However, the "New Age" is much more striking, much
freer, the universe responds to you, the energies, all this has
created a group of very, very staunch fans that is much more
understandable because nobody tells you: "You have to be like this or like that. "
You can believe what you believe, it is much freer and that
is linked to all this type of reiki pseudotherapies,
energies, auras, acupuncture, all this is closely linked.
So in parallel we see the discredit of
Catholic religion or morality with the rise
of this New Age spirituality as well. We see it
hey, for example, Netflix is ​​going to play the ... (Gwyneth Paltrow's show) I say:
"I can't believe it!" But it is real, Gwyneth Paltrow is one of the
standard bearers of the New Age and that also reflects as that
upper class, upper middle, American, when you have reached
your social status, then now I am going to play with
vaginal eggs and anal enemas and Yupi's World right? -Yes...
It's the reflection right? Because in the end it is the upper middle classes
that believe in this kind of thing.
-I also
think about something that puzzles me, and it's
scientists who are believers, or very respectful of religions.
Just as any scientist says about
homeopathy or even New Age religions or spirituality
they say, "No, that's all bullshit." But you say:
"Well, what about religion?" And they say: "No, there I ...er..."
What happens, this is for fear of losing followers, is it for fear of
confrontation, or what happens here?
-It's funny, of course.
-Do they really have that dissonance?
-I think so,
it is a dissonance, many are aware that it is a
dissonance, but let's not forget that in the end, well,
human beings need to believe in something and it is a belief, that is, it
is a need that is in most of us, not in others,
but it is something that is deeply rooted and it is very difficult to
pull that out, and in the end, all that unites us
, believers or not, is the fear of death, fear to
the unknown, and the fear of what comes next, that sometimes
overwhelms almost any rational person, who needs something to
hold on to to lead this better life, right?
So I respect that very much because I know that
it is difficult to live thinking that there is nothing afterwards or that this
is totally ... Some find it easier, others less, but
life in the end, well, is hard and is a winding road. Yes
, no? So, I understand, I respect that people who lead
their life in a rational way, are scientific and such, but
then say, well, I apart from that, I think there may be something
because of course, in the end what are we going to do? Do we eliminate
any beliefs from our life? Don't you believe in anything that
doesn't have any evidence? I believe that I do not believe in anything that does not
have any evidence. I mean, maybe I can trust something
but, if you ask me, for example about life after
death, I see it something completely absurd, without
meaning and I see so evident that a person or an animal or a
cockroach all come from the same do not? I see so
evident that there is no eternal life, that it is an invention ... Hm.
-But many people are not satisfied with thinking
that we are flesh and blood and a brain,
and it is normal, that is, it is difficult for all of us to understand how it is
possible that we are here. That we have conscience. That
we have conscience, all this, right? In addition, science
also takes us to certain points there with quantum physics
and all this that you say, well, this is fascinating, right?
That many people see God there. I respect it,
I understand it in a certain way although I do not share it because I
personally well it is the same right? I also think
that believing in something after death, well you can believe it but that
there is no evidence and that it is a belief about which you have to be
aware that there is no reliable proof
that it exists, I respect it.
-Of course. I also think about
agnosticism: It seems that when you say:
"Do fairies exist?" No, those are stories. "Are fairies and elves
fiction ?" Of course! "Are gods fictions?" Oh no,
there you have to be agnostic.
-Yes of course.
-Isn't that a trick? Because it is a way of saying: Look, I'm out, I do
not express myself. But we should be agnostic about everything!
Maybe we are not here and this is "Matrix".
-Of course, one you are agnostic...
-In other words, agnosticism rules only
when you talk about religion or a god.
-Absolutely. Yes, it is curious. But it is because it is so
ingrained in our society that it is much more difficult to
remove it, and also we all have relatives, friends who believe
in God and in fact with other scientific disseminators
we are all half divided, right? There are agnostic popularizers
and popularizers that we are more atheists, more staunch, right?
Like Crespo and myself. Yes, we are more
belligerent, but of course, they say that in the end
they do not know, so they prefer to call themselves agnostics.
But we don't know many things, the burden of proof has to be on who
affirms it, so if there is no proof for an affirmation, the
most logical thing for me is to be an atheist, well, a de facto atheist,
right? In the end I am not one hundred percent sure that God
does not exist, but the evidence makes me think that he does not, and I
live my life as if he were not, which is what
Richard Dawkins says in his book.
-People talk about respect for ideas,
religions, beliefs, such, and above all faith, faith
is respected , it is even said that it is a virtue.
How can you ...? Nobody cares what is true or not?
-Nobody cares about truth!
Impressive!
"Do you want to believe that later you are going to go to another world? Believe it, no problem. I don't only say: I do not believe it,
but I approve it, and I am complacent with your belief in this!" This seems terrible to
me because if we are complacent with these ideas,
we approve them, well then there's nothing to do,
there is no way to know what is real or not, what is true ...
-Absolutely!
I expected you to say: Yes, it does matter!
No, it doesn't! In fact, my TED talk is called "No one cares about the truth."
-You have come to the right place!
-Of course. But in all
aspects, that is, issues of religion, political issues,
everything, nobody really cares about truth.
Studies have shown that we are slaves to
our own opinions and our own beliefs and it is
very difficult to get ourselves out of there, even though we see
evidence to the contrary. Man, in terms of
alternative medicines and all this, we see the "it works for me" approach, it
is brutal. It doesn't matter if I show you fifty studies that tell you
that homeopathy does not work beyond
mere placebo. If it has worked for you, if it once
cured your cold, "but my cold
was cured in seven days "... Let's see, that's the
usual time it gets to recover from a cold. Yes Yes. But get
the idea out of his head that he was once cured with
homeopathy. And it's all like that: that is, if you once prayed
and the next day ... -you passed the exam ... you passed the
exam ... That was God. It's like these people who have had an
operation, prayed to God that it would be okay, leave the hospital
and say: "Thank God!" Man, thanks to the doctors who have
been doing the operation for twelve hours. -Correct. I say, no?
I think your God has done little there.
-Sure...  Beyond that,
I still think that of course there does not have to be
an immunity for any belief. Apart from,
as I have already said many times, respect for each other and that I
respect anyone who believes what they want to believe, that is
evident. But not being able to have a rational intellectual debate
and question the foundations of all that religion
that has been imposed on us throughout the centuries and that
still today has so much presence and does so much damage
in many societies ... and Spain is one of the more
respectful luckily, right? We live in one of the best
societies to be an atheist, but in other places being an atheist is persecuted
and is condemned up to the death penalty, then
the foundations of religion must be
questioned, the role of religion and
the church must be questioned, nowadays, and you don't have to have any kind of
-complacency, of complacency for a belief
beyond respecting that each one evidently
believes what he wants .
-Also the cost of religions
is immense. Here, for example, in Spain, I think that
the cost of the Catholic religion is
calculated about two hundred and fifty euros per person and year. We all
pay for that. And if you think of all those
resources used for something real... okay? Because from there a
small fraction goes to charity, which is what is said, right? "But this
is love, this is charity ..." Well, but twelve billion
euros do not go to charity. -Absolutely ... Shouldn't, only
for that, scientists, all reasoning people in general,
react and say: "Hey, we're using some
resources on something completely sterile, and something that just
gives you a placebo", but this placebo can be obtained in
many other ways, and it is not necessary ...
-Yes.
But I see it so far away and so impossible ... Of course I would
love it to be so. Not even the most leftist political parties
, the most atheist, position themselves very belligerently
against religion, because they are aware that a large part
of their electorate are believers, they are not going to get into that mess,
this is like everything. You don't get involved with football either,
because you know that everyone likes it.
You think: "I'm going to lose votes, it's going to be a fight that is going to
be lost, why am I going to do it?" I see it as something that
seems obvious to me, beliefs must be financed by
believers, whoever believes in it, not all of us have to
finance the beliefs, the problem is that many people still
believe in it, so it is vast majority of
society, those of us who do not believe are less. So, right now
, this battle is very lost, that is, I see it, I don't
know how you see it, I see it very, very lost. -Well, I see
there is ... I don't even see a battle, actually.
-I do see a
battle, for example, about religions leaving
school, people talk about that,
-People talk about that.
The mistake I see is that people say: "religions must
come out of school," And of course, religious people say: "why?"
Well, man, you will have to argue that because they are
false, that what they talk about does not exist, because if you
only talk about getting them out of school *, but there is not that
debate in which you say: "Hey, this is absurd..." ..
That incongruity is not shown,
nobody sees any contradiction,
well, I mean that nobody confronts these ideas,
so why should they be out of school *? Man,
because those are things that you have invented! We should say it
more clearly, I think.
-Sure, the issue of
religion in school is something that I see so
clearly, because in school you are going to learn knowledge,
feasible facts. -Of course. Scientific evidence, culture,
you are going to learn these kinds of things.
The way religion is taught today, it is pure dogma, pure doctrine.
-Yes.
I was hallucinating, when I received religious education at
school, I couldn't believe it! I would come home and
say: "They have taught me that Jesus did this and that..."
I asked my mother: Is this true?
Because, of course, they taught it to me until I was older, when I
could think a little, right? And I wondered: Is this true?
I was so puzzled that I was learning mathematics, geography and then they
were teaching me that Jesus is ... And they say: "You have to teach the
history of religions:" Well, that is integrated in the history
course , you have to teach. -Of course. In fact it is very
important to teach religion history to see how
religion has led us to very dark times in
history. So, I see it very important to teach the
history of religions, but it seems clear to me that religion
should be outside of schools. In fact, it is curious
because I have friends and people with whom I have debated on my channel
who are also Christians, but not Catholics, who have the same opinion as
me, who think that religion should come out of schools.
Because as it is taught, Catholic doctrine is also
imposed on other believers from other disciplines. So,
for them, the best thing is that it is not taught, and that each father and mother
if they decide to take their child to catechesis and all that,
then each religion is taught there.
-Of course.
This is something that seems obvious to me. Is the debate going to be fruitful
and is it going to come out? Okay. Is there any country in Europe? Yes,
in Iceland and all that does not happen. Yes. But they are few, right?
There is a change that is very curious. In Holland,
the biggest Dutch protestant church,
Forty percent of its priests and its parishioners
do not believe in Jesus Christ as something divine, they do not believe in God,
they do not believe in life after death! There is a priest
named Klaas Hendrikse ... -What are they, pantheists? No, no, they
simply follow Jesus Christ because of the doctrine, because
his ideas were cool, because of love, compassion, all
this, well, like someone who can follow Aristotle,
or Socrates. -Okay. But they don't believe, in fact,
this priest preaches from his pulpit, with his white
collar: "Enjoy this life because it is the
only life we have! Forget about stories... Jesus taught a
very good way of life
that we practice". They celebrate participatory masses of two hours
... Forty percent of that protestant church does not believe in a god! In fact, the guy has a book
called "Believe in a non-existent god." -Oh, how cool! Impressive.
So, there are changes that are taking place, right? And
there are also other areas of the world that live
in those dark times today in Muslim
countries, right?
-Absolutely.    Even look, you said:
"I received religious education." Let's see, education is what
you said it had to be:
critical thinking, freedom, reasoning, not obeying just because ...
Religion, is exactly (the opposite of *) all that.
And we talk about religious education and we have learned to see it that way.
It's impressive.
-Absolutely. What you
say, how nice what you say about Holland, because
I think one of the reasons why it is very difficult to
eradicate religion as such It is, at least in great mass, it
is because religions fulfill two functions that these
various authors say and it is so: one is, the belief in
the divine, in a superior being, but the other, very important,
is the feeling of community with people, right? That
in the United States is deeply rooted, peoples are
communities and they meet in the church, and if you
take that away from them , you take their life, that is, you take away their
friends, their community, their everything. And what you were telling me about Holland, I
see it similar because, although they do not believe in a superior being, they believe
in that community, and in that belief system that
makes them such. -Well, but those beliefs are totally
rational . Yes Yes Yes. -It would be fabulous, right? That would be great,
but in the end the feeling of community, in
the end atheists are like a gang of cats,
each one goes his way...
here we have cats off-screen but one is here lying, another one is playing ...
So , everyone is on his own, and that feeling of community is hard to have.
I see parallels everywhere. You know that I have also been to flat Earth events.
There I see a religion with absolutely all the details of what a religion is:
Everyone has a belief in something superior, which is no longer a god, but it is:
"They have deceived us, the earth is flat, we have the truth,
we have seen the light. " And on the other hand, the
huge feeling of a community that there is in something like this, I
told you, I was even welcomed at the event, and
I ended up eating a pizza, they ordered a
pizza like a flat Earth, with the flat Earth map.
They gave me a piece, then we were eating
around the pizza with beers and so on...
-Communion!
This is, come on, this is wonderful. So,
there I realized the feeling of community so strong that there is
in something, you see, like the flat Earth, but that
happens in everything. -Yes Yes. People need to believe in something and
feel part of something. In this, secular humanism
around the world is quite an important
organization with many, many associations.
In Spain there is hardly a very small association. But they
promote a rational, critical, scientific, and ethical
vision of life. They do their talks about
science, things applied to science, not only science
for the sake of knowledge, but science applied
to problems that affect as human beings, they also have
their charities,
And this may be an attempt, but for some reason it doesn't work.
At least here in Spain. In other countries, it does.
In Norway there is a powerful association
because it receives money from the state, just like * religions. -Of course.
This is a very complicated story.
But it is a community, they belong to that community.
Maybe we should, people who are "reasoners", more skeptical,
let's say about critical thinking ... Now, for example,
there is a certain sense of community with the people of
popular science. Maybe this community
should be a little more inclusive, including more
groups, right? And to say, no, I am skeptical like
these, reference people who speak clearly like you,
on all these issues, right? All: pseudoscience, religions, Gwyneth Paltrow ...
Yes, there are many, there are many people who are feeling welcomed by something
that until then had not felt, I notice it especially
with my audience in Latin America. Of course, in Latin America there is more
religious sentiment and in fact I find a lot of
barrier when I make videos about religion in that part
of Latin America. They tell me: "Okay,
homeopathy is a scam", then they say: "Hey, but with
religion, don't mess with it. " It is very difficult to remove that, because
you present it to him and you see that it is really parallel,
if this is a channel of critical thinking, of
questioning dogmas, beliefs, and such, everything goes in the pack
and I cannot ignore something as important as
religion, I can not.
It is so, but it is true that many other people in Latin America
have felt for the first time included in a feeling in a community like
"Wow, okay, beliefs have imposed on me all my life,
they have judged me for who I am, because of my religion, I have not been able to study,
well, because here we are talking about the most deeply rooted, more fundamentalist religion,
machismo, homophobia, and many other things. That there are many
people who have had to leave their families, because
they didn't accept them. Right? Then, they feel welcomed: "Wow.
Does this god really hate me for being who
I am for loving someone of the same sex? What's the point of that?"
And many people don't understand it, and they say: "
Well , now I am welcomed into another community", well that's
very good, right? We have to create a separate community,
because if not, we will never be able to combat the force of
Religion. It is impossible.
-Let's do it!
-We are working on it, little by little.
-"Before we discussed the subject of
death. I think (we should) talk about death, break that taboo,
because while death is not discussed and it is not
clearly talked about as the reality that it is,
many people say: Ok... But when faced with death, everyone gives in.
Everyone, even if they are not religious, celebrate a religious funeral
because there are hardly any non religious ceremonies in Spain,
which humanist associations are doing in other countries, they
do their non-religious ceremonies.
-Of course, this will be like weddings, in the end.
-I guess it will.
-Look at the plummeting that religious weddings have made.
But of course, the subject of death perhaps we should treat it more openly.
Explain that you can live, and be happy accepting the reality of death,
that you don't have to say: "Well, wherever you are ..." and all
this, that you hear, and people keep quiet. And say, "Hey, really
this ...", talk about it, both a public and private debate, right? -Yes.
For example, sometimes there are brothers who have different beliefs,
and when their parents die, one of them
believes that his parents are in heaven, unlike the other, and they never
talk about it.
-Absolutely.  It's very sad
that nobody talks about such an important matter:
-"How can you think this? Let's talk about it".
Well, ve are very afraid of
confronting ideas.
-Yes, talking about death
is so difficult, and when you have it near,
it's something so hard to cope with, that the last thing you want
is rationalising a subject that may bring more conflict
to families. So, people of course
choose not to talk about it, everyone sticks to their beliefs,
as long as you don't impose this or that to me...
right?  But then there are some quarrels.
-And there are some inforcements. For example,
maybe you have to attend a religious ceremony
or participate in certain events.
-Sure, sure...
-And in fact, you're paying for them.
-Absolutely, but as I told you, I think it's such a difficult subject to talk about...
I think there must be an intelectual debate
and we must normalize death, right? Because we are also
indoctrinated with that fear of death, aren't we?
"You must behave yourself in this life, because
after death you can have..." And a lot of people are
afraid of what may be after death
-Sure...
My philosophy is: "Do what you want in this world, as long as
you don't hurt others. Be as happy and
coherent as you can, and we will see if
there is something after death, probably not. So, live as
happily as you can without hurting others, I think
that is fundamental.
-Sure, I also think that people
think that if you're an atheist you are depressed. It's like:
"Well, you don't believe in anything..."  People think you don't have
morality or ethics, right?
-Sure
Then I say, if your ethics are forced on you by someone...
-That's what I say, I have created my own ethics,
it's not that anyone has told me what I must believe.
-But even so,
people think they are happier.
"How sad!" -I've been told. "So you believe you die and that's it?"
The first thing people say is: "You don't believe in anything?"
"-Then you die and that's it?" And I say:
Yes! What's the problem? The problem is people who are still alive.
But that people will also die one day, and in the end there'll be no problem.
So, in 500 years, none of us will have any problem.
Not us nor our relatives, like 500 years ago.
I see it so perfect...
I think that being atheists and not holding beliefs that creates cognitive dissonance,
allows us to be happier, because you can dare think what you want
you can get to know, be fascinated by being here, having developed a consciousness,
-And it eliminates fear.
and I think it is not made clear enough,
we should say: "Listen, you'll be happier if you abandon your beliefs, you simply
live your life, you are fascinated..." Because if you have those beliefs and dissonances,
you don't face the deep questions. When you have a conversation
similar to this one in a bar, it's like:
"Hey, you talk about any other thing, or I just go away...!
People don't even want to hear about all this.
But if you can talk about all this, you can at the same time see
the "grandeur" of all our knowledge, all we know.
-Sure.
We should do this. Well, you science popularizers do it,
Because you are very happy with your work.
-Sure, and we communicate it.
And you explain very clearly the values you get from it.
Well, I see that people like us,
who have a good life, no special worries,
we live in a "First World" country,
we can afford to think about this
and maybe live a fulfilled life being atheists
because my philosophy is:
I try to enjoy every day because I know that
life ends, I'm going to enjoy my time
and that doesn't make me less happy than a
believer, I don't see why it should be...
It's rather the opposite, I think that believers live with
fear of what there will be, always thinking:
"I'm not going to do this, because my god..."  I live free,
not being forced to anything, other than
my own ethics and morality.  But also, there are other
regions in the world where people are having hard lives,
people live almost in slavery,
they don't even have food, and sometimes their only relief is thinking
that after death there will be something better, that their god...
that they must bear these hard conditions, because there is something
later... And how can you tell these people: "Hey, you can be happy
without believing in a god".  The misery in which
so many people live... The only thing that prevents them from blowing up their heads
is thinking that there will be something better in an afterlife
and they'll be rewarded.  Then, from our
position, it's very easy to talk about a militant atheism,
but from other perspectives, I see it much more complicated.
-Yes. Maybe it could also be a reason to say: "Hey, you don't have another life
after this one." -Oh, then I dare start a revolution.  Right?
-Yes, it could be, too. There are both sides. It's true.
Well, there has also been some people who started a revolution,
the Arab Spring, "having a god with them".
Then the thing is to get rid of
the burden of thinking that someone
is watching everything we do,
judging if we are doing right or wrong, apart from your
own doctrine. I think that in the end, following a
religious doctrine makes you live permanently
like a minor, because you accept an external discipline
and you don't question for yourself what is good or bad,
and that is a problem. That is what we should enforce.
-How can we promote this compromise with critical thinking,
with not being passive?
-Good question.
There are a lot of aspects, starting from school,
and education, as we talked. Culture, scientific education,
critical thinking, teaching
boys and girls to question everything, because
in the end, if you teach children to question
if homeopathy works,
if reiki works, they won't stop there.
They will start to question everything:
religions, political power,
it's also very necessary, not believing everything
they say like parrots. Everything, you'll start
questioning everything they told us about economy,
how things work, everything. I think it's an active exercise
we must do, we have to practice all this, and above all
not being limited to our own ideological bubble,
that's very easy, and we do it.
I'ts very important, because many times
we have ourselves believed some fake-news because something sounds so good...
Even ourselves... What did you think?
"We believe that!" Be careful, we are also gullible, even
if we think a lot, all of us are gullible.
I always try to listen to
many of the approaches to a subjec, and following many different people,
with different opinions, because in the end, reading only authors
who think like you, listening to who thinks like you, is
very satisfactory. But reading the "enemy"
makes your beliefs wobble, that's what really puts you and your beliefs in check.
That's the good exercise, not believing that
you are always absolutely right, and you know everything
because then you are lost.
-Being in touch with all kind of..
-Of course
-Both types of believers...
-Of course, in my channel I'm very active
talking to people who think in a different way, because
in the end, we all have to live together, we have to get to
understand each other. And I think this is not incompatible, to try to build
a world where reason rules, and we can free ourselves from
dogmas as much as possible, we can talk to
all kinds of people, because we have to understand each other.
And people have their personal circumstances and beliefs
and we must understand and respect that.
-I hope that your work helps making it all possible.
-Yes, little by little...
-Do you want to say anything else?
-Well, it's been a pleasure being here, and it's been a very, very interesting debate.
-I think the same, thankyou very much!
-Thankyou, it's been great.